一哥们两小时喝了两升私酿酒，看看他眼睛怎么了。菜桑，31岁
A man drank 2L moonshine in 2 hours. This is what happened to his eyes. CS is a 31 year old man presenting to
送到急救室说浑身疼，恶心，看不清东西。他告诉值班护士他昨晚没睡好
the emergency room with body pain, nausea, and blurred vision. He tells the admitting nurse that he slept poorly the
肚子贼疼，之后开始视线模糊、扭曲
previous night and suffered severe abdominal cramps before seeing his vision distort and warp
前一晚菜桑参加了朋友新年夜“自带酒可劲喝”的活动
You see that previous night CS was participating with friends in a New Year's Eve BYOB Power Hour where each person
大家酒水自备，一小时内每分钟喝一小杯
would bring their own bottle of liquor and take a half shot on the minute every minute for a whole hour
菜桑不止想带自己的酒，还想带自己酿的酒。他女朋友几周前
CS didn't want to just bring his own liquor. He was going to MAKE his own liquor. He received a distillation kit a
送他一套酿酒器提前做圣诞礼物。他之前也酿过酒，就有点膨胀
few weeks prior as an early Christmas gift from his girlfriend. He had brewed his own beer before but wanted to move
上B站看了几个视频就想在家用谷物酿摩闪酒
towards moonshine, her homemade whiskey from grains after seeing some videos on the Internet
无证酿酒违反联邦的基本法，但他偏想试试，他认真按网上说的
Unlicensed distillation is federally unlawful but he thought to take his chances. He was sure he followed the
一步一步酿，酿好第一波之后刚好赶上朋友的新年活动
directions to ferment and distill correctly and didn't do anything wrong. As the batch was made, CS began the New Year
他也直说自己酿的一点都不好喝，毕竟
celebrations with friends. He didn't like the taste of his moonshine and was pretty vocal about it. After all it was
那酒整整80度，相当于他朋友带的四十度的两倍。菜桑和朋友关系还不错
160 proof or 80% alcohol, double his friends store-bought 80 proof liquor. He was a good sport and partied on with his
就和朋友接着喝，迎接新年，最后在两小时内
friends and they were having a great time celebrating the new years, and CS proceeded to finish all two liters
他自酿的两升酒也都喝完了。之后那晚菜桑感觉老难受了，感觉视线两边发虚
moonshine that he brought within 2 hours. As the night continued CS felt increasingly ill. His vision started vignette
发暗，一圈看不清。听觉也一团乱麻（这句你们自己体会）
darkening and blurring on the sides. His sense of sound began to flow into a sea of molasses as it slowed and warped
他寻思他喝了四斤80度的酒，肯定喝高了，啥都没吃
He thought because he drank 160 proof moonshine that he was just more drunk than normal. He went to bed not
就难受地上床了，第二天起床后他发现自己看东西发黑
eating anything but also not feeling great and as he got started the next day his vision quickly went dark
赶紧叫救护车去医院。在护士给
and he called for an ambulance where he's brought to the emergency room where we are now. Before the nurse can do a
菜桑做身体检查之前，菜桑想撒尿，去了十分钟都没回来
physical exam on CS, he has to use the restroom. He was in for about 10 minutes. The bathroom door still closed
医院的人想看看他没事吧，结果叫他没反应，最后进去发现他
Medical staff thought to ask and see if anything was wrong and when they received no response they entered and found
躺地上，口吐白沫，癫痫发作，蜷缩在厕所旁边。癫痫解决好之后
him on the floor foaming at the mouth and seizing as he was huddled over the toilet. As the seizure resolves he's
他瞳孔散大，对光无反应，呼吸每分钟28次，是正常人两倍
unresponsive pupils dilated and unreactive to light, respiratory rate 28 breaths per minute, double that of normal
昏迷指数（描述人意识的指数、暗示大脑损伤程度，越低意识越模糊）
His Glasgow Coma Scale, an objective measure of his consciousness, an indicator of brain injury is rated at
只有4，比完全昏迷高一分，说明他已经
just four, one point above complete unresponsive coma. There's indication here that he has
患上急性脑损伤，可如果菜桑只是喝多了
severe acute brain injury but something's wrong. If CS is suffering from just alcohol or
术语叫“酒精中毒”，那他是不会癫痫的。乙醇是神经系统的镇静剂
more formally ethanol intoxication then the seizure doesn't make sense. Ethanol is a nervous system depressant
它会取代兴奋神经递质，减慢大脑思考速度。而癫痫时他会抽搐
meaning that it slows down the brain and displaces excitatory neurotransmitters. Because he was convulsing during the
我们将此归为“全面强直－阵挛性发作”。T和C这两个词来自古希腊语
seizure, we classify it as generalized tonic-clonic. Tonic and clonic deriving from ancient Greek words tono's and
意思是抓挠、剧烈胡乱运动。G这个词代表癫痫
clonise which mean to stretch with violent and confused motion. Generalized meaning that the seizure which is a
这种过度兴奋状态已经影响到整个大脑了。这和酒精对神经系统的镇静作用是完全相反的
state of excessive excitation is affecting the entire brain. This is opposite of nervous system depression so
所以可以确认菜桑的癫痫和酒精没有直接联系。血检显示他血液pH值
we can say with certainty that ethanol is not directly responsible for his seizure. A blood test reveals that the pH
只有6.5，是正常的8倍酸，于是医院赶紧把他转到ICU
of CS is blood is 6.5, that's eight times more acidic than normal and is transferred to the intensive care
因为他罹患代谢性酸中毒。Osis指不正常，acid指提供氢离子的物质
unit as he's suffering from metabolic acidosis. "Osis" meaning abnormal state and acid being a chemical that donates
过多的时候会严重损害你的身体机能
hydrogen ions something when in large abundance can impair the normal function of your body
代谢性指这是由你的细胞代谢产能或者分解物质所引发的
Metabolic meaning that it's deriving from cellular processes that produce energy or breakdown substances
6.5的pH值，我们可以说菜桑患上了重度酸血症
With a pH of 6.5 we can conclude that CS is suffering from profound acidemia an acid presence in blood
如果菜桑昨晚除了两升摩闪酒和水之外什么都没碰
If since last night nothing entered CS's body except for two litres of moonshine and water
水和酒都不是强酸，除了撒点尿之外也没排出什么，那到底
neither of which are strong acids and nothing left his body except for some urine then how is it possible for so
血液里哪来的酸？摩闪酒里还有啥别的东西吗？Emmm有个高中生都懂的生物化学知识
much acid to be in his blood? Was there's something else in that moonshine. Well there's a bit of basic biochemistry
酿摩闪酒，要用到酵母发酵燕麦糖或者葡萄糖。发酵是细胞
to be known here to make moonshine CS used yeast to ferment oat sugar or glucose. Fermentation's the anaerobic or
无氧呼吸消耗葡萄糖的过程，得到粗产品叫"wash"，而葡萄糖是六碳糖
without oxygen consumption of glucose, producing an unrefined beer called a wash. Because glucose's a chain of 6
减去二氧化碳的一个碳，那么酿酒会生成戊醇以下的醇类
carbons, the yeast will produce alcohol chains of less than 5 after we account for carbon dioxide produced
也就是说有两个碳的乙醇是很常见的产物，在wash中占10~15%。也就是说
This means that ethanol at 2 carbons is very common yielding at 10~15% in wash. But it also means that
还会有甲醇这类摄入后对人类有害的产物。更惨的是菜桑喝的
the one carbon methanol which is not safe for human consumption is produced, too. And even worse CS used his
是他酿酒设备蒸馏浓缩后的80度的酒。蒸馏能把两种物质分开
distillation kit to produce his concentrated 80 percent ethanol drink. Distillation separates chemicals and is
首先要加热它们，乙醇沸点在78.3摄氏度，此时
started by heating the wash. Ethanol boils at 173 degrees Fahrenheit which means at this temperature it's vapor
啰嗦了一大堆说白了乙醇会
pressure is equal to the pressure exerted on it by the surrounding atmosphere, meaning it will face shift
沸腾汽化。水的沸点是100摄氏度，所以在78.3度时乙醇沸腾了而水没有
from liquid into gas. Because water boils at 212 Fahrenheit then heating to 173 boils the ethanol but not water turning
汽化的乙醇往上跑，然后冷凝液化重新收集起来
the alcohol into gas which will rise up in the still where it's collected condensed and cooled back into liquid in
就做出了摩闪酒。问题是甲醇的沸点是64.7度
a separate container creating moonshine. The problem with this is that methanol boiling point is 149 degrees Fahrenheit
比乙醇低，所以也会跟着乙醇最后冷凝进入摩闪酒里
lower than ethanol, so heating to 173 boils it to and collects and concentrates it into the moonshine
甲醇会先汽化冷凝，所以显然菜桑喝了不少甲醇
Methanol collects in the head or the first part of the distillate and it's apparent that CS drank a lot of it
而血检发现他甲醇浓度达到420毫克每分升，是资料记载
because a blood test reveals that the methanol concentration in his body is 420 milligrams per deciliter, more than 10
最小致死剂量的十倍。甲醇的物理与化学性质差别不大
times the minimum documented lethal dose. Methanol doesn't look much different from ethanol physically and chemically
菜桑80公斤，那么假设他全身有6L血液
Estimating his blood volume at 6 liters because of his weight of 80 kilograms measured at admission
说明他血液里有25克的甲醇。已知甲醇密度是0.8克每毫升
This means that there are 25 grams of methanol floating around in his blood. Given that the density of methanol is
说明他血液里大概有30毫升，两大勺的量
about 0.8g/ml, this means that there is about 30ml or 2 tablespoons full in his blood at the moment
甲醇和乙醇都属于弱酸，但30毫升肯定不至于让菜桑得酸血症
Like ethanol, methanol is also a weak acid but 30ml alone isn't enough to cause profound acidemia
甲醇在体内生理活性也不高，那到底菜桑是怎么回事的？
It's also physiologically inactive by self in humans so how could it be causing these problems in CS
回到刚刚的代谢性酸中毒，既然甲醇不是强酸
Well, let's go back to the name of his condition metabolic acidosis. If methanol isn't a strong acid then how
那甲醇是怎么代谢的呢？在人类体内，乙醇会被代谢两次，主要发生在肝脏
exactly is methanol getting metabolized. In humans, alcohols are metabolized twice, mainly in the liver
人类进化出这样的功能是因为肠道也有细菌在发酵
It appears that humans evolved this mechanism because the bacteria in your gut ferments sugars, that's the same
和菜桑用燕麦糖加酵母发酵一样，所以肠道每天会产生大概
fermentation that CS's yeast did with oat sugar and means that small amounts of alcohol about 3 grams are
3克的酒精。酒精的第一步代谢靠乙醇脱氢酶
produced in your gut every day. The first step of alcohol metabolism is where an enzyme called alcohol dehydrogenase
把醇变成醛。乙醛就是平常让人宿醉、脸发红的东西
converts it to aldehyde. Ethanol becomes ethanal which is responsible for hangovers and flushing while drunk
而甲醇会变成甲醛，就是造木乃伊那玩意，致癌
Methanol becomes methanal which is formaldehyde, used to involve mummies and is a likely carcinogen. This first step
这步代谢很快，所以会在体内积累乙醛，解释了晚上喝酒之后引发的宿醉感
is fast and causes a buildup of aldehyde in the body, explaining delayed onset of hangover after a night of drinking
第二步乙醛脱氢酶把醛变成羧酸
The second step is when aldehyde dehydrogenase converts aldehyde to carboxylic acid so ethanal is
乙醛就会变成乙酸，而甲醛会变成甲酸，这是主要毒物
metabolized to ethanoic acid which is vinegar but methanal is metabolized to methanoic acid which is a major poison
但菜桑的代谢性酸中毒不是因为甲酸中酸的部分，而是甲酸对
But it's not the acid moiety of methanoic acid causing CS's metabolic acidosis but rather the effect that it
身体的作用。你的细胞需要氧气，而细胞色素氧化酶
exerts on the body. Your cells need oxygen to produce energy. The enzyme cytochrome oxidase is a major part of
占很大部分，在代谢中需要大量氧气。而甲酸会与细胞色素氧化酶结合
this metabolism and relies heavily on oxygen to function. Methanoic acid binds into cytochrome oxidase and doesn't let
不让氧气进入细胞，强制细胞无氧呼吸，产生少量能量。当细胞
oxygen in and forces the cell to operate anaerobically and produce less energy all without oxygen. When cells are
无氧呼吸时，葡萄糖代谢产物是乳酸，高中生物都讲过
asphyxiated like this, they produce lactic acid from the glucose that they're trying to metabolize into energy
所以甲醇的代谢产物甲酸抑制细胞有氧呼吸，强制细胞
It's this methanoic acid being produced from methanol metabolism that's choking his cells of oxygen and forcing them
产生乳酸，使得菜桑代谢性酸中毒，进而酸血症。从目前情况来看
to produce acid causing CS's metabolic acidosis and profound acidemia. In looking at his physical condition
细胞的无氧呼吸对哪里影响最大呢？肌肉首先不会
where would this starvation of oxygen have the greatest impact? Well it's probably not the muscles since they're
肌肉就是耐乳酸的，剧烈运动，细胞无氧呼吸产生乳酸，过后肌肉酸痛这很正常
designed to tolerate lactate which is produced during exercise when a transient oxygen deficiency is common
肝脏问题也不大，因为它能处理、分解掉一部分，可是大脑呢？大脑
It couldn't be the liver as it can process and break down some of these assets but how about the brain? The brain
代谢非常活跃，短时间的缺氧
is metabolically active and short amounts of time with ischemic event when oxygen flow or utilization is blocked
会导致兴奋性中毒——大脑过度兴奋，会导致癫痫。菜桑脑部MRI显示
can cause excitotoxicity, an over excitation of the brain which includes seizure. A brain MRI for CS reveals hypoxia
他基底核——用来连接大脑主要部分——缺氧。另外，甲酸会被
or low oxygen in the basal ganglia which connects major parts of the brain together. Methanoic acid is known for its
眼组织选择性吸收，导致视神经细胞无氧呼吸
selective absorption into eye tissue and the optic nerve where it builds up starves the cells of oxygen and causes
从而导致坏死，甚至最后从里往外把自己耗死导致死亡。菜桑的眼部充血
them to necrosis or die as they literally digest themselves from inside out. Hyperemia or an abundant presence of blood
还伴有水肿，这都解释了菜桑
was found in CS's eyes along with edema or fluid swelling all explaining why CS's vision was
开始喝酒之后视力先恶化，之后到医院突然失明的症状
deteriorating since he started drinking and suddenly lost his vision as he presented to the emergency room
如果再晚一步，他就会永久失明，因为那时他的视神经因缺氧
If left untreated he will first go permanently blind as his optic nerve is choked out and depraved of oxygen causing
已造成不可逆损伤。之后他的大脑会出血、坏死
irreversible nerve damage. After that his brain will begin to hemorrhage and bleed out and necrosis as it starves
一滩大脑在一滩死亡的脑细胞里渴望氧气。这类通过影响酶来产生对身体有害因素
for oxygen and swims in a pool of its own dead cells. The notion of enzymatic activity modulating or causing toxicity
的问题我在生理学里见得多了。一氧化碳和氰化物都有
by its action or lack thereof is a recurring physiologic theme. Both carbon monoxide and cyanide have the same
和甲酸类似的原理。它们阻止氧气和细胞色素氧化酶结合
mechanism as methanoic acid. They block oxygen from binding to cytochrome oxidase preventing cells from using
从而阻止细胞的有氧呼吸，让细胞产生过量乳酸，引发代谢性酸中毒、坏死、最终死亡
oxygen causing an overproduction of lactic acid causing metabolic acidosis, necrosis, and eventually death
有时候医生会给你开“前体药物”，这类药刚吃的时候是没用的
Medicines are sometimes given in pro-drug form meaning that they're inactive when taken orally but metabolized
只有经肝脏代谢之后的产物才有用。比如降压药依那普利，会被转化成有生物活性的
by the liver into active form. For example, the blood pressure medication enalapril is converted to biologically active
依那普利拉，抑制血管紧张素转换酶，阻止血管紧张素I
enalaprilat which inhibits the angiotensin converting enzyme, preventing activation of the hormone angiotensin
转换为血管紧张素2，从而降低血压。这个灵感来自于巴西蝮蛇
one to its vasoactive form lowering blood pressure. This specific use case in humans derived from the Brazilian pit
它的毒液能让小型哺乳动物的猎物血压降低到致死的地步
viper whose venom was designed to fatally lower blood pressure of its prey, typically of small mammalian descent
也就是说只要是哺乳动物，这招就好使。当狗吃巧克力时，它们会摄入过多可可碱
meaning that the idea of enzymatic activity transcends species. When dogs eat chocolate they consume theobromine
一种很像咖啡因的物质，会导致颤抖，是一种兴奋剂。人类在肝脏
a chemical similar to caffeine that causes tremors and acts as a stimulant. Humans metabolize theobromine
有酶代谢可可碱，但狗没有，就算有代谢也很慢
in the liver enzymes but dogs do not have these enzymes so they break it down very slowly if at all, meaning that
所以可可碱会在狗身体里积累，造成兴奋过度，提高心脏收缩程度，提高肾上腺素水平
the theobromine accumulates causing over stimulation, increasing heart contractility, increasing adrenaline levels
接着体温高、肌强直、战栗、癫痫，最后死亡。如果是甲醇的话，效果就反过来
causing hyperthermia, rigidity, tremors, seizures and death. With methanol, the exact opposite is happening
甲醇生理活性低，只有轻度镇静作用，而且互溶于水
Methanol is physiologically inert and only produces mild sedation. It's already water soluble meaning that it can
说明可过肾而进于尿液。但它的代谢产物有毒。如果酶能
dissolve in the urine as is and be excreted by the kidneys. But its metabolites are poisonous. If enzymes can
像细胞色素氧化酶那样被甲醇抑制，那有没有办法抑制甲醇
be competitively inhibited like cytochrome oxidase, is there a way that we could prevent methanol from binding
和乙醇脱氢酶结合从而阻止甲醇被肝脏代谢呢？有的。乙醇和乙醇脱氢酶
to alcohol dehydrogenase and stop it from being metabolized? Yes. Ethanol binds to alcohol dehydrogenase
结合能力比甲醇强，所以乙醇自己就能阻止甲醇和酶的结合
with a greater affinity than methanol and it does so competitively meaning that it will prevent methanol from ever
从而阻止甲醇的代谢。这也解释了为什么菜桑
binding to the enzymes active site preventing it from metabolizing. This explains partly why CS's symptoms were
在昨晚还醉、血液里有乙醇的情况下症状没那么明显，所以甲醇的解药
more mild while he was still drunk the previous night with ethanol still in his blood, and it means that the antidote
就是乙醇。给他上透析，同时注射碳酸氢钠缓解
for his poisoning is more ethanol. He's put on dialysis as well as given sodium bicarbonate, a base to correct his
酸中毒，同时10%乙醇输液，时刻监视血浆甲酸浓度
acidosis, a 10% ethanol IV infusion is administered, plasma methanoic acid concentrations were monitored and shown
在注射乙醇之后甲酸水平明显降低了，同时缓解的自然还有他的代谢性酸中毒
to fall after ethanol administration, along with spontaneous resolution of his metabolic acidosis and improvements in
人也精神不少。文献资料里写透析结束后体内甲醇半衰期是
his mental status. As documented in the literature, the elimination half-life of methanol in the body after
54小时，甲醇会通过肾脏，不经过代谢，直接以尿液形式排出
discontinuation of dialysis was 54 hours as methanol dissolved in CS's urine, and was excreted through the kidneys
避免了代谢产物甲酸，救治及时的话，甲酸影响酶而造成的细胞缺氧
unmetabolized, halting the production of methanoic acid, if caught early, can reverse the ischemic and hypoxic damage
的损伤范围不大，也会得以修复。菜桑的故事
caused by the poison as enzymes are not consumed in the chemical reactions in which they participate. CS's story is a
也很好的解释了美国联邦法律不允许私酿酒
fine example for reasons why alcohol distillation without permit is federally unlawful in the United States
另外在全世界各地旅行的时候，也别乱喝便宜的酒精饮料
It's a common international travel tip to be careful of cheap liquor and some country's because it could have been
那些三无产品可能有不少甲醇，年年害死多少人
bootlegged and adulterated to be contaminated with methanol, poisoning hundreds if not thousands of people as
几毫升就能中毒，造成不可逆损伤。再之，乙醇也被用于
the toxicity and irreversible injury can happen in as little as a couple milliliters. Furthermore ethanol was used
汽车燃料，蒸馏的蒸汽高度易燃
as car fuel at one point in time. It's vapors generated during distillation are spontaneously combustible
而蒸馏时还要加热，所以密封不好的话很容易爆炸。美国所有州2015年酒精税收
Because distillation requires heat, poorly sealed stills will explode. US alcohol tax revenue including all states in
70个亿，占当年联邦总税收3250亿中的0.2%
2015 was counted at 7 billion dollars, or 0.2 percent of the 3.25 trillion dollar total federal revenue of that year
就算私酿酒合法化，推广开来，而且要上税，也不太可能
Even if personal distillation were lawful, popular and taxed, it's not likely
和工业大规模酿酒的品质相媲美。所以别说合不合法
home production would even come close to matching the volume produced industrially. So isolating the reason for
就说政府税收体制都没整明白，还会因此埋下
distillation laws - just saying that the government cannot tax it - is incomplete and neglects the fact that this has
甲醇通过蒸汽毒害更多人的隐患
potential to harm a large number of people chemically through methanol poisoning and physically through ethanol vapors
在ICU的治疗与监视下，菜桑和他的朋友们
With proper treatment and monitoring in the intensive care unit, a strong lesson learned and why making
在摩闪酒很危险、私酿酒违法这些事上上了深刻的一课。而后菜桑也痊愈了
moonshine is dangerous and unlawful by him and all his friends, CS was able to make a full recovery
感谢观看，祝大家身体健康！
Thank you so much for watching. Take care of yourself and be well